Preliminary Guide to the Mary M. Geran Starr Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Mary M. Geran Starr papers
1910-1960
MS 459
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2.5
Correspondence, printed matter, photographs and memorabilia reflecting the friendship of Mary Geran with members of the Greek royal family and with members of the German nobility. The largest number of letters are from Lilo Scholz, Marguerite, Landgräfin of Hesse, Grand Duchess Helen of Russia and from Sophia, princess of Greece.
Starr, Mary M. Geran
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mary M. Starr in 1941-1960.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
These papers of Mary M. Starr contain correspondence, printed matter, photographs, and memorabilia.
The bulk of these papers consists of correspondence and other papers relating to members of the royal family of Greece of whom Mary Starr was a personal friend. The persons represented by the largest amount of correspondence are Prince Nicholas (1872-1938) and his wife, Princess Helen (1896-), and Landgräfin Marguerite of Hesse (-1954). Also included are short writings by Pince Nichola, an annotated copy of his memoirs, My Fifty Years, and photographs of family members, Greek schools and hospitals, and paintings by Prince Nicholas. There is also correspondence with individuals not related to the royal family, much of it dealing with the royal family and Greek affairs, although some of the correspondence seems to be from individuals Mary Starr met in China and Japan. There is, finally, printed matter and memorabilia relating to the British royal family, and a list of parcels sent by Mary Starr to members of the Greek royal family and others over a period of five years.
These papers were given to Yale University by Mary M. Starr between 1941 and 1960.
Biographical / Historical
Educator; M.A., Yale, 1930; from 1915-1916 taught in Japan; 1919-1922 liaison agent between warring factions of North and South China; ca. 1922 married Harry M. Starr; ca. 1942-1945 provided home for British sailors on leave in the New York area; in 1947 awarded "The King's Medal for Service in the Cause of Freedom,"; taught French in Indiana, 1947; taught in Leesburg, Virginia, 1960.
For a chart outlining the genealogical relations of the Greek Royal family, please consult the Genealogical Chart.
Europe; Greece -- Kings and rulers; Frederika, Queen, consort of Paul I, King of the Hellenes, 1917-1981; Geōrgios, Prince of Greece, 1869-1957; Helen, Princess, consort of Carol II, King of Rumania, b. 1896; Helena Vladimirova, Grand Duchess of Russia, Princess Nicholas of Greece, 1882-1957; Marguerite, Princess of Prussia, Landgräfin of Hesse, d. 1954; Marina, Duchess of Kent, 1906-1968; Sophia, Princess of Greece, Princess Christoph of Hesse, Princess George of Hanover, b. 1914; William, German Emperor, II, 1859-1941; Scholz, Lilo; Starr, Mary M. Geran
- Inventory
  - Greek Royal Family and Related Individuals
    - Frederika Louise, princess of Hanover, consort of Paul I, king of the Hellenes (1917-), 1950-1958 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - George, prince of Greece (1869-1957), 1951 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Helena Vladimirovna, grand duchess of Russia, princess Nicholas of Greece (1882-1957), 1941-1957 (Box 1, Folder 3 - 7)
    - Helen, princess of Greece, consort of Carol II, king of Rumania (1896-), 1937 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Marguerite, princess of Prussia, Landgräfin of Hesse (-1954), 1935-1953 (Box 1, Folder 9 - 20)
    - Marina, princess of Greece, duchess of Kent (1906-1968), 1950-1954 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Nicholas, prince of Greece (1872-1938)
      - Correspondence, 1928-1940, undated (Box 2, Folder 22 - 37)
      - My Fifty Years, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Olga, princess of Greece, princess Paul of Serbia (1903-), 1950-1951 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Richard, prince of Hesse, 1948-1955 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Sophia, princess of Greece, princess Christoph of Hesse, princess George of Hanover (1914-), 1948-1954 (Box 3, Folder 41 - 42)
    - Theodora, princess of Greece, Margravine of Baden, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - William II, German emperor (1859-1941), 1936 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Other indiviudals
    - Calligas, Mr. and Mrs. Paul, 1935-1939 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Contostavlos, Angelique, 1938-1947 (Box 3, Folder 46 - 47)
    - Empson, Marie Kimstadios, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Kuroda, Meiko, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Moses, George H. (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Quo, Mme. Diana H., and Quo Tai-Chi, 1932-1960 (Box 3, Folder 51 - 55)
    - Rankin, K. L., 1946 (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - Scholz, Lilo (Mrs. H. W.), 1940-1941 (Box 3, Folder 57 - 62)
  - Printed matter
    - "Constantin 1er inconnu," La Petite Illustration, no. 731, 1935 July 13 (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - George V, king of Great Britain: silver jubilee souvenir bookletsSee: Box 4, oversize, 1935
  - George VI, king of Great Britain: coronation programs and souvenir booklets, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 64)
    General
    See also: Box 4, oversize
  - Starr, Mary M.: newspaper clipping, 1943 April 4 (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Photographs, 1910-1947, undated (Box 3, Folder 66 - 71)
  - Starr, Mary M.: notes on parcels sent to members of the Greek royal family and others, 1947-1952 (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Oversize photographs and printed matter (Box 4)